A Guide to the Papers of John McLaren McBryde, 1900-1907
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
- Requisition Orders, 1907-1908. (Box-folder 4:139)
  - m: Requisition orders of the Department of the Infirmary, 1907.
- Reports on Delinquent or Unsatisfactory Students, 1907-1908. (Box-folder 4:140)
- Original Documents from folder 140: Reports on Delinquent or Unsatisfactory Students, 1907-1908. (Box-folder 4:141)
- Cahill-Clevinger, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 4:142)
  - a: Letter referring to the bad condition of the diploma the student received.
  - b: Various correspondence with Dr McBryde concerning information about V.P.I.
  - c: Letter from the War Department. Office of the Chief of Engineers acknowledging V.P.I. being added to the approved list of technical schools.
  - d: Letterhead from the Jamestown Exposition requesting a preliminary sketch of the V.P.I. exhibit.
  - e: Letters form the acting president, 1907.
  - f: Letter discussing the dairy exhibit proposed to the Jamestown Exhibition, 1907.
  - g: Letters from the State Board of Agriculture and Immigration concerning the plan of re-organization, 1907.
- Original Documents From Folder 142: Cahill-Clevinger, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 4:143)
- Clothier-Cuthorell, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 4:144)
  - a: University Record, February 1907, "Agriculture" Published quarterly by the University of the State of Florida, 1907.
  - b: Notable letterhead from the University of the State of Florida with a photograph of the Department of Agriculture and Horticulture, 1907.
  - c: Business card for Geo. A. Cole, Professor of Agriculture at the University of Arkansas, 1907, Cole was applying for a position teaching Agronomy at V.P.I.
  - d: Notable letterhead from Commercial Printing Company Incorporated, 1907.
  - e: Notable letterhead from The Lutheran Orphan Home of the United Synod of the South, 1906.
  - f: Notable letterhead from Credential Employment Corporation, 1907.
  - g: Advertisements with photographs of miss Nellie Amber Crossen, entertainer, reader, lecturer in lecture-recitals, popular entertainments and fictional readings. Includes press evaluations and personal endorsements.
- Original Documents from 144: Clothier-Cuthorell, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 4:145)
- Dabney-Dwight, McBryde/Barringer, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 4:146)
  - a: Notable letterhead from Jamestown Exposition includes resolution from the General Council.
  - b: Letters form the House of Representatives about H.R.. 24757 and Association of Colleges and Preparatory Schools of Virginia, Including the Constitution and By-Laws, 1908.
  - c: Letter to Mr. J.J. Davis, appointing him instructor in the Department of Modern Languages, 1906.
  - d: Notable letterhead from Appomattox Trust Company, 1907.
  - e: Notable letterhead from the Dickey Drug Company, 1907.
  - f: Casino Technical Night School, blue print of tally of students including, number of students attending, Nov. 1, 1906, 2, Comparative table of enrollment and 3, percentage data table, includes also a letter from the president, C.R. Dooley, explaining the statistics and their significance.
  - g: Letter referring to the arrangements of Hilcrest, 1907.
  - h: Letter referring to the newly proposed rule of making four years the required commitment to the military work in the institution, 1907.
- Earhart-Everett Waddy Co., McBryde/Barringer, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 4:147)
  - a: Letter to J.D. Eggleston about the duties of the president, 1907.
  - b: Letter from the State Superintendent Public Instruction, 1907, requesting information of the rules and regulations governing the board at V.P.I.
  - c: Notable letterhead from Ford's Hotel, 1907.
- Fain-Fuqua, McBryde/Barringer, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:148)
  - a: Questionnaire form Harvard University St. Paul's Catholic Club with response from V.P.I.
  - b: Notable letterhead from Franklin County Telephone Co., 1907.
  - c: Business Card for Fitz-Hugh, Luther Co., 1906 for railway equipment.
  - d: Correspondence with Catholic family concerning the facilities at Tech & ways to improve them, 1907.
  - e: Correspondence with Dr. Fletcher about building up the Agricultural side of V.P.I.
  - f: Notable letterhead from Bridgewater College, 1907.
  - g: Letter stating exact costs of V.P.I., 1906.
  - h: Invitation to visit Hampton Normal and Agriculture Institute, 1907 during the Jamestown Exposition explain the foundation & management of the institution school for Negro & Indian races.
  - i: Correspondence regarding McBryde's resignation & the open position of presidency.
- Gaines-Guy, McBryde/Barringer, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:149)
  - a: Official V.P.I. explanation from, 1907, asking to take Stock Management and Practice in Breeding instead of French and Wood Working.
  - b: Letter from Atlantic Coast Line Railroad Co. Office of Passenger Traffic Manager 1906, discussing the students fare and a new federal law.
  - c: Notable letterhead from the National Freight Service Association, with the Origin of the National Freight Service Association on the back of the letterhead.
  - d: Letter from the House of Representatives of The United States, Carter Glass.
  - e: Notable letterhead from Grimes Bros. Merchant Millers, 1907.
  - f: Notable letterhead from Nasseau Orchards, 1907.
- Original Documents from 149: Gaines-Guy, McBryde/Barringer, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:150)
- Haas-Herron, McBryde/Barringer, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:151)
  - a: Notable letterhead from Hammond Typewriter Co., 1907.
  - b: Letter from the United States Department of Agriculture, Office of Experiment Stations, talking about the creation of a Department of Extension Work at V.P.I., and asking for the advise of the Board of Visitors, 1907.
  - c: Notable letterhead from Guggenheimer & Co. Inc., 1907.
  - d: Letter to the University in reference to the terms of the deed for the Camper property and how the University has failed them, 1906.
  - e: Notable letterhead from Ongersoll-Rand Company, 1907.
  - f: Notable letterhead from the State Board of Agriculture and Immigration.
- Heard-Hydraulic Press Mfg. Co., 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:152)
  - a: Letter from the South Park, Methodist Episcopal Church, recommendation for Mr. H.D. Hemenway of the Hartford School of Horticulture, from Elmer A. Dent.
  - b: Letter inviting McBryde to a series of talks given at the Carnegie House to the men who were members of the clubs and to the prospective young voters.
  - c: Lecture schedule for the Home Culture Clubs, course in gardening, H.D.Hemenway, titles, times and subject material of each lecture being given.
  - d: Letter referring to the unsanitary condition of the sewer line between the infirmary and Agriculture Hall, 1906.
  - e: Notable letterhead from Virginia Pilot Association, 1907.
  - f: Letter confirming the nomination of Mr. S.M. Herrick as Assistant Chemist of the Experiment station, 1906.
  - g: Notable letterhead from Army and Navy Department of the International Committee Young Men's Christian Association, 1907.
  - h: Letter discussing the changes that took place in the Geology department, 1907.
  - i: Letter from Dr. McBryde before his retirement recommending Dr. Holden to the Board of Visitors, 1907.
  - j: Letter from a parent in reference to the poor food served to the students at Tech and the alternatives, with response from the acting president.
  - k: Letter from McBryde about a boy wishing to resign due to homesickness and Dr. McBryde's advise on the matter including a statement from the president concerning looking after the boy if he stays and making sure he makes friends who encourage him to stay, 1907.
  - l: Correspondence in regard to the restructuring of the English department, including proposal of possible division of work, 1907.
  - m: Letter from Iowa State College concerning the expansion at V.P.I. instruction staff, with recommendations, 1907.
  - n: Correspondence referring to the tents as living quarters for the students, 1907.
- Original Documents from folder 152: Heard-Hydraulic Press Mfg. Co., 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:153)
- Irving-Jenkins, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:154)
  - a: Letter referring to a short course during the winter break for farmers, 1907.
  - b: Letter referring to the acceptance of Prof. S.W.Fletcher to be the director of the Experiment Station and professor of Experimental Agriculture, and the work being done there.
  - c: List of military experience from J.S.A. Johnson for Commandant, 1906.
  - d: Correspondence with the War Department, Office of the Chief of Ordnance, Washington, about the ammunition and orders made by V.P.I., 1906.
  - e: Letter referring to the Grand Camp of the United Confederate Veterans of Virginia's reunion, and asking for the Cadet military band to play, 1906.
  - f: Letter referring to the firing of explosives form the barracks, an account of the event, 1907.
  - g: Notable letterhead from Virginia-Carolina Stave & Lumber Co. Inc., 1906.
- Jenkins-Joynes, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:155)
  - a: Letter from the Commonwealth of Virginia Department of Public Instruction State Board of Examiners, 1906.
  - b: Letter referring to Mr. Campers interest in the water rights, 1907.
  - c: Letter from McBryde recommending Dr. Barringer for promotion into full professorship, 1907.
  - d: Letter to Dr. McBryde in regard to the fees for representation of the University for the Christian Case, 1906.
  - e: Letter referring to the Grand Camp of the United Confederate Veterans of Virginia's reunion, and asking for the Cadet military band to play, 1906.
  - f: Letter referring to the firing of explosives form the barracks, an account of the event, 1907.
  - g: Notable letterhead from Ardie-Tynes Manufacturing Co., 1907.
  - h: Form from the University of Pennsylvania Alumni catalogue committee, 1906, requesting information on Dr. George G. McBryde.
- Original Documents from folder 155: Jenkins-Joynes, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:156)
- Kaatz-Kyle, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:157)
  - a: Notable letterhead from Staunton Military Academy, 1906.
  - b: Letter from McBryde regarding to work being done in the " Negro interest," reference to work done by McBryde on the subject, 1907.
  - c: Notable letterhead from Kimball & Rogers Printers, 1907.
  - d: Notable letterhead from Tidewater Publishing Co., 1907.
  - e: Notable letterhead from Student Volunteer Movement for Foreign Missions, 1906.
  - f: Notable letterhead from Edward's Mining Company, 1907.
  - g: Notable letterhead from The Stoddard, 1907.
- Lachicotte-Lueckel, McBryde- Barringer, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:158)
  - a: Notable letterhead from R.A. DePriest, Plumbing and Tinning, 1906.
  - b: Notable letterhead from The Kavanaugh Bros., 1906.
  - c: Notable letterhead from Lane Brothers Company, 1907.
  - d: Letter from the House of Representative, Washington in response to a letter from McBryde, 1907.
  - e: Notable letterhead from M.H. Lash, 1906.
  - f: Inspection and insurance report from the Hartford Steam Boiler, Inspection and Insurance Company of Hartford Connecticut, on the condition of the Steam Boiler at V.P.I., inspected on August 16 & 17, 1907.
  - g: Notable letterhead from The Investor's Title, Trust & Realty Co., 1906.
  - h: Letter referring to a suit of the Central Manufacturing Company, dealing with Col. Patton before he died.
  - i: Notable letterhead from the M.C. Lilley & Co., 1906.
  - j: Notable letterhead from Joseph Dixon Crucible Co., 1906.
- Original Documents from 158: Lochicotte-Lueckel, McBryde- Barringer, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:159)
- Mabey-McCoy, McBryde-Barringer, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:160)
  - a: Letter including an abstract of experience from T.O. Mabry, professor of Natural Sciences at Winthrop College, South Carolina, 1907.
  - b: Notable letterhead from the Southern Bagging Co.
  - c: Printed statement in regard to the Army Longevity pay which accrued prior to February 24, 1881, sent from Herbert and Micou Attorneys at law.
  - d: Notable letterhead from Ainsle & Martin manufacturers Agents, and Jobbers of, 1906.
  - e: Notable letterhead from Atlantic Coast Line Railroad Company, 1906.
  - f: Letter form Mr. H.L. Maynard in the House of Representatives in reference to a bill to develop and promote Agriculture and Dairy production in Virginia, 1907.
  - g: Application and Resume of Dr. Rufus M. Bagg Jr. Looking for a job in the Geology department, 1907.
  - h: Notable letterhead from New River Pocahontas Consolidated Coal Company, 1907.
  - i: Letter from the School and College Bureau about openings of six jobs in engineering, 1906.
- Original Documents from folder 160: Mabry-McCoy, McBryde-Barringer, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:161)
- McBryde Miscellaneous. (Box-folder 5:162)
  - a: Letter from the Board of Visitors accepting his resignation and naming the date for it to take place, 1906.
  - b: List of discussions at the meeting of the Executive Committee, Septemeber 7, 1906.
  - c: Report of the Institution for the current session written April 6, 1904.
  - d: Official note to the Treasurer, concerning the changes in salary.
  - e: Minutes for a meeting of the Board of Visitors, 1906.
  - f: Report of Appropriations and Expenditures since 1891.
- McCoy-Myers, McBryde/Barringer, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:163)
  - a: Letters from the faculty in reference to the refrigeration machine.
  - b: Notable letterhead from J.S. Walker Lumber Company, 1907.
  - c: Letter from the War Department, Bureau of Insular Affairs in Washington regarding the 300 vacant teaching positions to be filled in the upcoming spring in the Philippines, 1907.
  - d: Letter from the War Department, Bureau of Insular Affairs in Washington, requesting the names of former students qualified for twenty positions teaching various technical subjects in the Philippines.
  - e: Information letter about a male industrial teacher position for Philippine Service with information concerning the Service and the job included, 1907.
  - f: Publication from the Government of the Philippine Islands, Department of Instruction, Bureau of Education: A Statement of Organization and Aims Published for General Information, 1906.
  - g: Notable letterhead from the Hotel Wachapreague, Island House Ocean Front, 1907.
  - h: Letter from the North Carolina Trust Company, includes sales pitch about guaranteeing loans.
  - i: Notable letterhead from Randolph Macon Academy, 1907.
  - j: Invitation to the Thomas S. Clarkson Memorial School of Technology, Potsdam, New York, Founders Day Celebration, November 13, 1906.
  - k: Letter from Frank Mills, Department of Geology and Biology at St. Lawrence University referring to a vacancy in the geology department at Tech, 1907.
  - l: Notable letterhead from The Miller Allaire Co., 1906.
- Neal-Nyman, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:165)
  - a: 1905 Original newspaper copy of the Virginia Polytechnic Institute advertisement.
  - b: Notable letterhead from Arkansas Agriculture Experiment Station, 1906.
  - c: Notable letterhead from the Neostyle Co., 1904.
  - d: Letter from the News Leader in Richmond, VA discussing the new rule at V.P.I. forbidding students to correspond with the newspapers.
  - e: Correspondence with a mother whose son received a gun shot wound in the thigh and was under the care of the school surgeon, 1907.
- Original Documents from folder 165: Neal-Nyman, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:166)
- Oakes-Owens, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:167)
  - a: Notable letterhead from Stephen Putney Shoe Co., 1904.
  - b: Notable letterhead from The Oliver Typewriter Company, 1906.
- Pace-Pearson, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:168)
  - a: Notable letterhead from the Pacific Era, a Japanese newspaper for the Japanese students at the University, 1907.
  - b: Letter from the University of Virginia Dean, J.M. Page with question about young men's interest in a liberal education and desire to know the numbers.
  - c: Letter from an alumnus working for Star Electric Company, asking if the school was interested in a fire alarm system, 1907.
  - d: Letter to a parent with list of expenditures, 1907.
  - e: Notable letterhead from The National Association of Audubon Societies, 1907 referring to the protection of wild birds on farms because of their economic value.
- Original Documents from folder 168: Pace-Pearson, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:169)
- Pearson-Quillen, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:170)
  - a: Letter from Dr. Newel Perry a former instructor of Mathematics at the University of California seeking possible employment with V.P.I., 1908.
  - b: Notable letterhead from Penn and Rison Tobacco, 1907.
  - c: Correspondence with Charles E. Picot Printing Co. with acceptance of bid by V.P.I. for the printing of the catalogues, 1907.
  - d: Letter from the Bureau of Education regarding the year end report, 1907.
  - e: Various correspondence in reference to students being able to work their way through college.
  - f: Letter from the United States Department of Agriculture, Bureau of Plant Industry, with a recommendation for the directorship of the Virginia Experiment Station, 1907.
  - g: Letter making an offer to Mr. Charles Piper with statement about fighting to build the agriculture school, 1907.
  - h: Notable letterhead from Poehlmann & Schnepfe Lumber, Coal and Mill Work, 1906.
  - i: Letter from Norfolk and Western Railway Co. including questions for the University to fill out and return, 1906.
  - j: Notable letterhead from Suffolk Packing Co. Inc., 1907.
  - k: Letter from Secretary of University of Virginia concerning some photographs of V.P.I., 1907.
  - l: Letter from the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching, asking particular questions about the income of the institution during certain years, 1906. (With reply from V.P.I. a few letters later.)
- Original Documents from folder 170: Pearson-Quillen, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:171)
- Excused Absences, (Ca. 500 discarded), 1907. (Box-folder 5:172)
  - a: 118 formal excuse forms filled out by various students for the year 1907.
- Ramey-Robeson, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:173)
  - a: Letters referring to changes in the plumbing for the Dairy Department of the Agricultural building and the costs of the change, 1906.
  - b: Notable letterhead from The Union Blacking Co. Inc., 1906.
  - c: Breakdown of students and their religion as answers to questions posed by the General Secretary, Chas. A. Reese, 1906.
  - d: Notable letterhead from The United States Wood Preserving Company, Manufacturers of U.S. Wood Blocks, 1906.
  - e: Correspondence in reference to a possible opening in an instructors position, 1907.
  - f: Notable letterhead from "The Antlers," at Colorado Springs, 1906.
  - g: Letter to Mr. F. L. Robeson stating his appointment to instructor in the mathematic department, and discussion of the benefits and salary, 1906.
  - h: Notable letterhead from the Electric Bank Protection Company, 1906.
  - i: Letter accompanied with program for the Mississippi Agricultural and Mechanical College Cadet band concert, 1906.
  - j: Letter from Mr. Robeson accepting the position and the offer made to him to become a mathematics instructor at V.P.I., 1906.
- Salder-Snyder, McBryde/Barringer, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:174)
  - a: Letter from the Assistant Secretary for the Department of Agriculture in D.C., recommending the candidate, Professor E.P. Sandsten to succeed Director Soule, 1907.
  - b: Letter from the Clark Teachers' Agency making recommendations for the open position of Dean and Director of the Virginia College of Agriculture, 1907.
  - c: Letter from the Maryland Agricultural College with recommendation for E.P. Sandsten for the opening in the Agriculture department at V.P.I., 1907.
  - d: Letter referring to a short course and the way to get farmers to attend, 1907.
  - e: Letter from W.D. Saunders about the exposition and how V.P.I. is doing, also a personal request regarding the poor servant help he and his wife were receiving, 1907.
  - f: Letter from the Roanoke Industrial and Agricultural Association, 1906 inviting McBryde to the Great Roanoke Fair, (letter included free passes.)
  - g: Letter about the Jamestown Exposition that opens April 26, 1907 and closes November 30, 1907, (Notable letterhead.)
  - i: Letter referring to the Second Convention for the Southern Conference on Immigration and Quarantine being issued by the Governor Jno. I. Cox, being held in Nashville, 1906.
  - j: Letter from henry E. Shepherd asking for McBryde to promote the sale of his new book titled The Life of General Robert E. Lee, 1906.
  - k: Notable letterhead from the Southern Planter, the leading agricultural journal of the south, 1907.
  - l: Letter from The Sherwin-Williams Co. referring to a sample of Medicinal Linseed Oil that was sent to V.P.I. for testing, 1907.
  - m: Letter to Mr. Stanley Shugert regarding the Honor System at V.P.I., 1907.
  - n: Letter and response about waste water runoff onto Mr. Sites property, 1907.
  - o: Notable letterhead from Mitchell-Powers Hardware Co. Incorporated, 1907.
  - p: Letter covering the expenses for the trip to Jamestown for the exhibition, 1907.
  - q: Letter from the president concerning the case of Stolen property from a store room, 1907.
  - r: Notable letterhead from the Smoot Advertising Agency, 1906.
- Original Documents from folder 174: Salder-Snyder, McBryde/Barringer, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:175)
- Sommerville-Syfan, McBryde/Barringer, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:176)
  - a: Letter from Mr. Soule after his resignation in regard to receiving money for services rendered, 1907.
  - b: Letter from A.M. Soule confirming the acceptance of his resignation, 1907.
  - c: Notable letterhead from the Southern Stamp and Stationary Co., 1906.
  - d: Advertisement for rubber stamps for business includes pictures, Watkins- Cottrell Company, 1909.
  - e: Notable letterhead from the Boston Badge Company, 1907.
  - f: Complimentary Season ticket to the International Live Stock Exposition accompanied with a business card form Mr. J.A. Spoor, 1906.
  - g: Letter from C.H. Spooner, President at Norwich University urging president at V.P.I. to call congressmen in protest to a legislation "authorizing the appointment of extra officers in the Army in numbers sufficient to permit the detail of an officer on the active list to each of the 100 schools and colleges throughout the United States," 1907.
  - h: Letter concerning the same legislation as stated above from the Wentworth Military academy in Lexington, Mo., 1907.
  - i: Notable letterhead from The American Sabbath Union, letter concerning the change in hours of recitations, and urging Sunday to be a day of rest and worship, 1907.
  - j: Notable letterhead from The Sterling's Pharmacy, 1906.
  - k: Notable letterhead from The Virginia Bridge & Iron Co., 1906.
  - l: Letter from J.A. Stiver including his experience and educational background seeking employment as faculty at V.P.I., 1907.
  - m: Letter concerning how the expenses are divided on the trips that the boys at V.P.I. take, in response to a complaint from a parent, 1907.
  - n: Letter from P.F. Stout seeking employment at V.P.I. in the Languages, includes experience and educational background, 1906.
  - o: Letter to Gov. Claude A. Swanson in regard to a criminal investigation, letter presents the information on both sides of the case, 1907.
  - p: Letter from the Virginia Governor Swanson inviting the V.P.I. cadets to be in a parade at the unveiling of the monument dedicated to President Davis in Richmond, 1907.
- Original Documents from folder 176: Sommerville-Syfan, McBryde/Barringer, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:177)
- Talbott-VanCourt, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:178)
  - a: Letter from M.K.Taliaferro, with suggestions on how to run the library so it is more useful, 1905.
  - b: Notable letterhead from The Decatur Chamber of Commerce with map on the back, and photographs of different buildings.